Guide to the Stanford University, Department of Computer Science, Stanford Computer Forum Distinguished Lecture Series, Videorecordings V0058
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
- Videorecordings
  - The Users Speak Out--A Customer's Perspective of Computer Science, by William Miller (Moderator), Dr. Peter Castro, Kodak, Peter Dietz, General Electric, Michael Rose, US WEST, Dr. Bruce Johnson, and Arthur Anderson. Part 2., 1988-02-10; V0058.081; 1 videotape(s) (U-matic) (Box 14)
    Computers and information systems are playing an increasing role in society, including fields that lie outside of science and engineering. In many of those fields our ability to implement new systems that provide increased capacity is limited by the state of the art in computer science and engineering. In many areas we know that we need a better understanding of the underlying science and technology (e.g, distributed systems) in order to design and implement leading edge systems. The panel session will provide an opportunity to raise issues of common interest to the academic community and our technologically oriented society as a whole
  - The Alpha Syntauri Synthesizer. a New Concept in a Musical Instrument Project, by Ellen V.B. Lapham and Robin J. Jigour., 1981-10-14; V0058.082; 1 videotape(s) (U-matic) (Box 14)
    The alphaSyntauri instrument is a modular, programmable digital synthesizer system based on the Apple II micro computer. The driving philosophy behind its design is the use of digital technologies to achieve flexibility, reliability and expandability in a compact and cost effective package
  - An Extension to the Programming Language C for VLSI Layout, Ph.D. Oral of Kevin Karplus. Edited master., 1982-07-28; V0058.083; 1 videotape(s) (U-matic) (Box 14)
    CHISEL is a systems language for building VLSI design tools. It can be used directly for designing chips, or for writing PLA generators, graphics editors, placement and routing systems, or full silicon compilers. CHISEL programs produce libraries of CIF (Caltech Intermediate Format) cells, together with header files providing essential extra information (cell names, sizes, connection ports, ... ). These headers provide all the information necessary for other CHISEL programs to use the cells. Utility programs exist for linking libraries, checking library consistency, plotting, .... The library structure gives strong support for hierarchical design styles. Named connection ports can be defined in any cell and copied with appropriate transformation when cells are placed or replicated. Simple but powerful primitives are provided for drawing wires and transistors. These form the basis for creating cells, and for interconnecting them. A new concept (fringes) is introduced to handle a variety of routing problems. An automatic wiring mechanism for non-permutation routing is provided using fringes.
  - Concurrent Testing at the Computer System Level, Ph.D. Oral of Masood Namjoo., 1982-11-08; V0058.084; 1 videotape(s) (U-matic) (Box 14)
    This study establishes improved techniques for on-line detection of computer malfunctions. In contrast with the classical techniques for detection of errors at the circuit level, the techniques in this study use the information about the overall system behavior for the purpose of error detection. Such information is extracted from the program definition and is given to an auxiliary low-cost processor, called a watchdog processor. The watchdog processor uses this information in order to detect abnormal system behaviors. Several techniques are explained for monitoring system attributes such as execution flow and data access using a watchdog processor. The architecture of a general purpose watchdog processor called CERBERUS-16 is described. Techniques for concurrent testing at the microprogram execution level are developed. In these techniques the microprogrammed control unit is modified so that it is possible to detect a large percentage of sequencing and microcode errors.
  - Copyright, Patents and Trademarks, by Dr. Donald J. Chesarek., 1983-02-02; V0058.085; 1 videotape(s) (U-matic) (Box 15)
    Copyright, patents and trademarks are formal mechanisms to protect intellectual and industrial property. The presentation will start with a review of basic concepts with a historical perspective and move to a discussion of current requirements based on easy to remember examples. Scenarios from the speaker's development experience will be used to illustrate how development problems can arise and some of the recovery techniques used to minimize rework. Understanding the basic concepts is fundamental to problem avoidance during the development cycle and legal problems after the product has shipped.
  - The New Generation Software Technology as Represented by the LISA System, by John Couch and John Love., 1983-02-16; V0058.086; 1 videotape(s) (U-matic) (Box 15)
    The Apple LISA is an integrated software and hardware personal computer system designed for the non-programmer. LISA features an iconic (picture-based) programming environment which models closely the office environment LISA is intended to support. Technical problems plagued this talk by John Couch and John Love; the camera was unable to capture a truly readable image of the demonstration on the machine and during the early portion of the talk there were sound problems. Still, the talk itself and the questions afterward are of interest. The talk is followed by a professionally filmed demo provided by Apple[, "in which the graphics are excellent."]
  - Constraint Propagation Techniques for Theory-Driven Data Intemretation, Ph.D. Oral of Tom Dietterich. Edited master., 1984-10-25; V0058.087; 1 videotape(s) (U-matic) (Box 15)
    This talk defines the task of THEORY-DRIVEN DATA INTERPRETATION (TDDI) and investigates the adequacy of constraint propagation techniques for performing it. Data interpretation is the process of applying a given theory T (possibly a partial theory) to interpret observed facts F and infer a set of initial conditions C such that from C and T one can infer F. Most existing data interpretation programs do not employ an explicit theory T, but rather use some algorithm that embodies T. Theory-driven data interpretation involves performing data interpretation by working from an explicit theory. The method of local propagation of constraints is investigated as a possible technique for implementing TDDI. A model task--forming theories of the file system commands of the UNIX operating system--is chosen for an empirical test of constraint propagation techniques. In the UNIX task, the "theories" take the form of programs, and theory-driven data interpretation involves "reverse execution" of these programs. To test the applicability of constraint techniques, a system named EG has been constructed for the "reverse execution" of computer programs. The UNIX task was analyzed to develop an evaluation suite of data evaluation problems, and these problems have been processed by EG. The results of this empirical evaluation demonstrate that constraint propagation techniques are adequate for the UNIX task, but only if the representation for theories is augmented to include invariant facts about the programs. In general, constraint propagation is adequate for TDDI only if the theories satisfy certain conditions: local invertibility, lack of constraint loops, and tractable inference over propagated values. There are some annoying "blinks" in this tape. However, they do not detract from the content of the lecture.
  - Knowledge Engineering: Artificial Intelligence Research at the Stanford Heuristic Programming Project, Produced and Directed by Anne Feibelman. Edited master., 1985-02; V0058.088; 1 videotape(s) (U-matic) (Box 15)
    This twenty-minute film has been chosen for the United States Pavilion at the 1985 World's Fair at Tsukuba, Japan.
  - Multi-Level Logic Array Synthesis, Ph.D. Oral of Christopher Rowen. Edited master., 1985-06-12; V0058.089; 1 videotape(s) (U-matic) (Box 15)
    Automatic synthesis of VLSI logic circuits from function descriptions creates the opportunity for vastly reduced design cost, but presents formidable challenges. This silicon compilation requires a four step translation: 1) writing the function in terms of available logic components; 2) minimization of this logic representation; 3) mapping of logic into the target technology's circuit primitives; and 4 )selection of a detailed layout configuration. Existing methods based on programmable logic array (PLA), standard cell and gate array topologies attack the problem by placing severe restrictions on logic structure or circuit topology. A new method based on multi-level logic and Weinberger arrays integrates the entire compilation from functional description to layout generation, and provides greater flexibility in logic minimization, circuit topology and design goals. Multi-level logic and Weinberger arrays serve as ideal partners in synthesis of large circuit structures. Deeply nested logic expressions can save exponential area, power and circuit delay over sum-of-products form, and Weinberger arrays can directly implement the arbitrary interconnections of these complex logic functions.
  - Implementation of Resilient. Atomic Data Types, by Prof. Barbara Liskov. The first of two lectures given by Prof. Liskov on two successive days. Edited master., 1986-01-29; V0058.090; 1 videotape(s) (U-matic) (Box 16)
    A major issue in many distributed programs is how to preserve the consistency of data in the presence of concurrency and hardware failures. A promising approach is to implement the programs in terms of data types with two properties: their objects are atomic (they provide serializability and totality for the activities that use them) and resilient (they survive hardware failures with high probability). The talk discusses issues that arise in implementing such atomic types and describes a particular linguistic mechanism provided in the Argus programming language. The approach is illustrated with several examples.
  - Specifications of Distributed Programs, by Prof. Barbara Liskov. The second of two lectures given by Prof. Liskov on two successive days. Edited master., 1986-01-30; V0058.091; 1 videotape(s) (U-matic) (Box 16)
    Distributed programs frequently have performance requirements, such as high availability and concurrency. To accommodate these requirements, designers often change the functional behavior of the program from what it would have been in the absence of the requirements. The result is a program whose behavior is difficult to describe. This talk discusses how to give user-oriented, informal specifications of such programs. The specifications are given in a notation that distinguishes the expected and desirable effects from undesirable ones. This distinction makes the specifications easier to understand and is informative for both the users and the implementors of the program. To illustrate the approach, the talk will include example specifications of several distributed programs that have been described in the literature.
  - "Important Areas of Computer Science Research as Seen from an Industrial Viewpoint, by Dr. Elliot PinsonPinson, AT&T Bell Labs; Dr. Janusz Kowalik, Boeing Computer Services Co.; and Dr. George Dodd, G.M. Research Labs, Panelists of the 18th Annual Meeting of the Stanford Computer Forum", 1986-02-04; V0058.092; 1 videotape(s) (U-matic) (Box 16)
    This Panel Discussion was sponsored by the Eighteenth Annual Meeting of the Stanford Computer Forum. At the Seventeenth Annual Meeting in February, 1985, the industrial members of the Forum requested a greater interaction between the academic and industrial participants. Each participant opened with short remarks, followed by a panel discussion involving the audience and the panel's industrial participants. No constraints were placed on topics of discussion. The Forum member participants indicated those areas of computer science which they considered particularly important as research topics worldwide.
  - An Overview of Expert Systems, by Dr. Doug Lenat. Master., 1986-05-14; V0058.093; 1 videotape(s) (U-matic) (Box 16)
    Dr. Lenat describes ways that artificial intelligence, specifically expert systems, will codify the body of common sense knowledge so that it can be used for problem solving and knowledge acquisition. Lenat presented the lectures at a Hewlett-Packard workshop, courtesy of the Computer Forum. H-P has graciously made the tapes available to us for the Distinguished Lecture Series.
  - Common Sense Knowledge, by Dr. Doug Lenat. Edited Master., 1986-05-14; V0058.094; 1 videotape(s) (U-matic) (Box 16)
  - "The Transition of Computer Science Results to Business and Industry, by Dr. Richard Shuey, Moderator; Dr. Thomas Buckholz, PG&E; Dr. William Spencer, Xerox Corporation; Dr. Gordon Bell, NSF, Panelists of the 19th Annual Meeting of the Stanford Computer Forum,", 1987-02-04; V0058.095; 1 videotape(s) (U-matic) (Box 17)
  - The Social History of the Personal Computer, Lee Felsenstein, 1989-06-07; V0058.096; 2 videotape(s) (U-matic) (Box 17)
  - Algorhithm Automation, Marc Brown, 1988-09-28; V0058.097; 1 videotape(s) (u-matic) (Box 17)
  - Microprocessors in the Works from Motorola, Russell Stanphill, 1989-05-24; V0058.098; 1 videotape(s) (vhs) (Box 17)
  - Efficient Debugging of Parallel Programs, Bart Miller, 1988-03-30; V0058.099; 1 videotape(s) (vhs) (Box 17)
  - Legal Issues, Tom Vinje, 1988-12-07; V0058.100; 1 videotape(s) (vhs); 2 videotape(s) (U-matic) (Box 18)
    Mr. Vinje discusses legal issues concerning the protection (copyright protectability of computer software, covering areas such as look-feel and interface compatibility.
  - Viruses. Worms. and Other Distributed Computations, John Shoch and Jon Shapiro, 1988-11-09; V0058.101; 1 videotape(s) (U-matic) (Box 18)
    The network virus widely reported in the press the last few days is one example of distributed computations. The speakers will discuss the history of such distributed computations and the specifics of the particular virus recently found and eradicated.
  - The NeXT Computer, Craig Hansen, 1988-10-19; V0058.102; 1 videotape(s) (U-matic) (Box 18)
    The NeXT Computer was introduced on October 12 after a three-year development effort. The design of the NeXT Computer reaches breakthrough advances in cost and performance and provides a feature-rich computing environment that uses high-quality graphics and sound along with a large library of software and literature. The talk will describe the hardware systems of the NeXT Computer, including the processor card, backplane and other expansion interfaces, the Megapixel Display, the 400 DPI Laser Printer, and the 256 Megabyte read/write/erasable optical drive.
  - KEYKOS: A Secure Object-Oriented Operating Systems, Norm Hardy, 1989-02-08; V0058.103; 1 videotape(s) (vhs); 2 videotape(s) (U-matic) (Box 19)
  - RISC vs. CISC; Old vs. New, Nick Tredennick., 1989-04-05; V0058.104; 2 videotape(s) (u-matic) (Box 19)
    Tredennick discusses trends in microprocessor architecture and development, including the current RISC fad. If RISCs succeed, it's on the strength of their implementations and in spite of the weak theoretical base. The RISC "breakthrough" is packaging the idea: changes to the architecture are a technology advance. The real issue is new architecture vs. old architecture. These ideas compete in a new field, with a weak experimental and theoretical base, developing under intense commercial pressure. The next microprocessor implementations will feature: register relabeling, distributed control, out -of-order execution, deep pipelining, write reservation queues, branch prediction, and multiple instruction issue.
  - Computer Science as Seen from Industry, panel discussion., V58.104; 1 videotape(s) (u-matic) (Box 19)
  - The Architecture and Implementation of the Intel 486, John Crawford and Ken Shoemaker, 1989-05-03; V0058.105; 2 videotape(s) (vhs) (Box 20)
    Intel 486 processor provides a 2.5 to 3 times performance gain over the 386. In this talk the microarchitecture of the 486 will be described, the various functional blocks and their interconnecions identified, the pipelining within the execution and address calculation units explained, and the performance of the on-chip cache examined.
  - Intel's 960 Superscalar Architecture and Future Implementations, Steve McGready, 1989-05-10; V0058.106; 1 videotape(s) (vhs) (Box 20)
    Mr. McGeady will present a brief overview of Intel's 960 architecture, and will present technical details of a new implementation of that architecture that allows the dispatch and execution of several instructions each clock cycle. The detailed micro-architecture of the core processor will be desribed, as well as the macro-architectural considerations that enable such an implementation.
  - Conflicts of RISC Architecture in Real-Time Control, Kim Rubin, 1989-05-17; V0058.107; 1 videotape(s) (vhs) (Box 20)
    RISC architecture trades away consistent performance for statistical performance. Large register sets, cache memory, and other features, are diametrically opposed to the short context switching time and low latency needed by real-time CRT) control systems. Specific requirements that result from how embedded computers are used in real-time systems should dictate critical underlying architectural design.
  - Architecture and Design of the i860 64-bit Microprocessor, Les Kohn, 1989-04-12; V0058.108; 1 videotape(s) (vhs) (Box 20)
    Semiconductor technology and CAD tools have reached the point where it is possible to develop 1,000,000 transistor microprocessors. Conceived to take full advantage of this technology, the i860 CPU is a single chip, 64-bit RISC based microprocessor which uses parallel instruction execution and supercomputer architectural concepts. To achieve balanced performance, one third of the chip area is devoted to integer instructions, one third to instruction and data caches, and one third to floating point and 3-D graphics support. The talk will review architectural goals as well as implementation considerations.
  - The MARS Hardware Accelerator, Prathima Agrawal, 1989-04-26; V0058.109; 1 videotape(s) (vhs) (Box 20)
    This talk will focus on three aspects of MARS (Microprogrammable Accelerator for Rapid Simulations). First I will describe the architectural and design details of the machine. Second, I will present the logic simulation algorithms that have been implemented and are in production use today. Lastly, I will show the versatility of MARS for solving graph search problems by describing how MARS pipelines could be set up to accomplish other CAD and some of the non-CAD applications such as connected speech recognition.
  - Link-Time Code Modification, David W. Wall, 1989-02-01; V0058.110; 1 videotape(s) (vhs) (Box 20)
    The language system for DECWRL's Titan and MultiTitan rests on an optimizing back end called Mahler. Mahler does some of its optimizations at link time rather than compile time, because more global information is available then. Nevertheless, these optimizations are optional; the Mahler compiler produces correct code that can be linked in merely traditional manner. To achieve this, we have developed a terminology of link-time code modification. Link-time code modification is proving useful in performance analysis and architectural modeling as well.
  - Backplane Bus Design, Paul Borrill, 1989-01-18; V0058.111; 1 videotape(s) (vhs) (Box 20)
    This lecture is designed to give an overview of some of the theoretical and practical issues in backplane bus design. Topics covered will include transmission line effects, the bus drivng problem, synchronization domains, spatial and manufacturing skews, clock latency, split vs non-split transactions, arbitration methods, the byte-ordering problem, and protocols to support cache consistency along with general bus architecture models.
  - Toward a Gigabit National Network: Technology and Policy, David I. Farber, 1989-01-25; V0058.112; 1 videotape(s) (vhs) (Box 20)
    Over the past two years major forces have been at work shaping the future of communciations networks (in particular data networks). These forces have been both political and technological. In the political arena, the success of the NSFNet in the support of science has focused the attention of policy makers on where the nation must be in the year 2000. Several reports including one from the National Academy have outlined possible directions. In the technological arena the development of switching architectures capable of handling the variety of traffic anticipated and the rapid deployment of fibers have changed the complexion of the field. This talk will explore both areas and will also explore the impact of the gigabit world on the computer field.
  - Workstation for the '90s, Andreas Bechtolsheim, 1989-04-19; V0058.113; 1 videotape(s) (vhs) (Box 21)
    Mr. Bechtolsheim discusses the goals, design, and implementation of SUN's new SP ARC workstation, pointing out a number of its features.
  - CAD Applications of Massive Parallel Computers, Alberto Sangiovanni-Vacentelli, 1989-03-01; V0058.114; 1 videotape(s) (vhs) (Box 21)
    Massively parallel computers such as the Connection Machine developed by D. Hillis at MIT offer a new paradigm for CAD algorithms which allows the exploitation of fine as well as coarse grain parallelism. Two CPU intensive CAD problems have been attacked with the Connection Machine: process simulation and device simulation. As submicron geometries require that simulations be performed in three dimensions, the computational requirements increase dramatically. This talk will focus on the relationships between algorithms and massively parallel architecture.
  - VorTeX, a Multiple Representation System, Michael Harrison, 1989-03-08; V0058.115; 1 videotape(s) (vhs) (Box 21)
    There are two basic types of document processing systems, source-based (like TeX) and direct manipulation (a la MacWrite). VorTeX, for Visually Oriented TeX, is a multiple representation document processing system which has some features of both types of processors. In this talk, we will show a video tape of VorTeX, a companion system called IncTeX as well as a Postscript interpreter built at Berkeley. We will discuss some of the design, implementation, and performance issues.
  - Debug: a Multiprocessor Debugger for UNIX System V, Jonathan Shapiro, 1989-03-15; V0058.116; 1 videotape(s) (vhs) (Box 21)
    Better integrated networking and the rapid proliferation of network-based applications is pushing us toward the need for multiprocess debugging across heterogeneous architectures. This talk describes Debug, a prototype developed internally at AT&T Bell Laboratories to explore the issues in this sort of debugging. Debug supports multiple source languages, and can debug both sides of a client-server application in which the server is running on one architecture and the client on another.
  - The Computer Forum Panel Discussion: Issues in Distributed Computing, 1989-02-15; V0058.117; 1 videotape(s) (vhs) (Box 21)
    The costs of computing, memory, and mass storage continue to drop at a rapid rate. To date, that rate has been much more rapid than any reduction in communications costs. Added to these economic trends are advantages to the user and information system developer of local control and operation. The rise of micro "main frames," microcomputers, personal computers, and work stations illustrate the overall trend to distributed computing. At the same time, there will continue to be a need for central computing and data services. It is important that we understand the issues, and tradeoffs, in designing future distributed systems.